a continuation of a radio series on mind
control that we're bringing you. Um, we heard
uh for the last five weeks a lecture and interview
by Dr. Colin Ross uh detailing the history of
CIA's mind control experimental programs that
are have been documented by uh and uh documents
obtained by the Freedom of Information Act.
What we're going to hear today is the mind
control testimony that was introduced into the
presidential advisory committee on into the
presidential advisory committee on human radiation
experiments in May uh rather March 15th of 1995.
President Clinton has apologized and compensated
some of the victims of the radiation experiments.
At the end of the hearing, however, Valerie Wolf,
Claudia Mullen, and Christina Colola gave their
testimony about mind control experiments and
linked in with the radiation experiments. We're
going to hear that testimony that was given
to the advisory committee. In the second half
of the show, in the first half, we're going to
hear Claudia Mullen talk about the experience
of giving testimony at the presidential
hearings. Claudia is a survivor of CIA mind
control experimentation for many years and uh got
introduced to this through the two lane university
which we heard Colin Ross talk about two lane's
involvement in the mind control programs in the
previous weeks here. It's extremely brave
of these women to have come forward and
uh they really in effect had uh broke the silence
for many survivors. You're listening to 88.1 CKLN.
But when she leaves the room, her life
is never the same again because she's
been asked to give testimony in front of
a presidential committee on radiation.
And that's pretty much what I
wanted to to to tell you all was um
what the experience was like. Um and I have some
some clips from the the testimony and um to show
you. And then um I don't know if you know y'all
got handouts but they're not complete but anyhow
um what are we doing on time? Oh okay. Well,
anyhow, um she walks in the room and there's
obviously a lot of uh important people there and
but there's also just a lot of everyday people.
Um people of all ages. The only people that are
missing are children. There aren't any children
there. But it's a good good thing because the
stories that she hears, people that get up
ahead of her, tell their stories, they're pretty
heart-wrenching and she forgets to be nervous for
a while because they just move her so much.
But then finally it's her she hears her name,
she realizes, oh, I have to give testimony. So
she goes up and um she gives her testimony and
they ask her questions and when she leaves the
room all of a sudden everybody knows her name
now and people just start swarming all over
her and um telling her how brave she is and
she feels scared to death and she can't figure
out why everybody thinks that she's so brave.
Um, she got up and told her story about the
monster mom and about the magister and about
the camp and about the cabins of Deep Creek Lodge
place. Um, told him everything. And I forgot to
tell you how she remembered because remember
I said that she um that I always um forgot
everything. As soon as I got home, it would,
you know, I would forget what what had happened.
And that went on. When I went away to college, I
still had no memory of it, you know. And then in
um October of 92, something happened to me.
Completely unrelated. Had nothing to do with any
of this. Just just another crime that, you know,
in a a city that has a lot of crime actually.
But a man comes into her home, a man that she
knows, and um he assaults her, he rapes her,
and he keeps her for hours, and he beats her.
And it becomes, she thinks it's the worst thing
that's ever happened to her, but somehow it's
really familiar feeling. And after that day,
all of a sudden, she starts getting all these
horrible nightmares and memories and flashbacks.
and she didn't even know what a flashback was,
but flashbacks start coming and um it pretty much
triggered all the memories that started coming
back. And so by the time she goes to Washington um
she's only about halfway through doing the
memories. So it's really kind of hard when
she gets up to talk about it um because she has
to control, you know, not to go into a flashback
when she's talking about it. But it it works
out okay. And after that um I have to say life
was never the same again. From then on uh there
was no going back once I did once I did it. Um,
I had to stay. I had to keep talking cuz if you
stop talking, that's when they get you because
um there are a lot of um to be honest,
there's a lot of good things in there.
There's some bad parts about um testifying. The
good part is that she got to tell her story. Um,
people believed her. She was asked to to tell her
story and because when the memories started coming
back and she went into treatment to therapy,
um the imaginary friends, they woke up after
all these years. They woke up again and they came
out and they would start writing um furiously. I
mean pages until it it came well into a book about
this big and all of her memories, all the people,
all the places that she went, um what the
people's titles were, who they worked for,
how much money they got, if they anything that
they talked about, whole conversations. Um,
and she sent off the information to various
experts across the country who tried to verify
as much as they could. And lo and behold, there
was a lot of stuff in there that wasn't written
down anywhere that um hadn't been released yet,
but they think that is in the CIA files. But um
so it's good that she gets to to get up and tell
her story and every time she tells her story it's
a little more healing. It's it's therapeutic
but um it also gives other people a chance to
tell their story because it it kind of starts
something going. And ever since that day, um,
people have started to talk about what happened.
And she's met so many other children that are now
grow grown up and they're starting to remember.
And she knows she's not alone anymore cuz all
those years, even though she didn't remember a
lot, she was felt really alone and she thought
special meant alone or odd. And um I guess you
could say the bad part is that like I said once
you testify it becomes public record. And the
good part is that you can't be sued because
um no matter what you you know as long as you're
telling the truth and that's that's what I did.
um you making accusations against people, but
they can't sue you because you're testifying and
um it's the truth and from then on all you can
talk about the same people as much as you want
and they can't ever sue you. So that's one thing
I've never had to worry about is being sued. But
I've been threatened and harassed and assaulted
since it happened. And um I wouldn't be telling
the truth if I if I said everything had been
just great since then cuz there have been some
bad times. But had I to to do it all over again
knowing what would have happened, I wouldn't
change a thing. I'd still do it. Just do it in
in a second. Only I would do it after I finished
doing my memories. After I got all my memories
back. That's the only thing that I would change.
And um let's see there anything else?
Huh? They wouldn't postpone the hearing,
would they? No, I tried to get
them to, but they wouldn't.
Um Oh, yeah. And another reason that it would
have been better if I had recalled all my memories
before I testified is because what I didn't
realize was they used a lot of time distortion um
along with the drugs and the electricity and the
trauma. Um they used hypnosis and it distorts they
could distort time and so and it also uh somehow
it gets you to confuse people cuz they they
thought well if there's a slight chance that she's
going to remember at least you'll get up things
all confused. Plus they throw in a few things
like uh ceremonies and things like that just to
so you'll sound really crazy if you ever start
to remember. Um, and so my testimony would have
been a little more accurate as far as, you know,
there's a few distortions in there, a few um, like
mixing people's names with the wrong wrong face.
But once I got all my memories, then I remembered,
you know, exactly. And then, but I can't change
testimony. Once it's given, it's given. Um, so I
thought maybe you all would like to see a a little
clip from it. I didn't I didn't bring my testimony
because as you can probably imagine, I don't like
to see myself on film. I don't mind having my
picture taken, but I really can't stand to watch
myself on film. And I guess you know why. So, uh
I mainly just wanted to kind of give you an idea
of what it looks like and um because hopefully
in the near future there'll be um a commission
for victims of mind control. This was focused
on radiation and we were allowed to to testify
because and there were three of us, well actually
four of us that were victims of mind control, but
they used radiation and I was I guess you could
say one of the lucky ones because they didn't use
a lot of radiation with me and they took a lot of
X-rays because I got hurt a lot but uh with
some mind control victims that they use a lot
of radiation um and that's how we got to testify
in front of a radiation commission. But hopefully
that's what we're trying to do is um that's what
the whole movement is about. But you know what we
got started is we're trying to get a committee
on our to investigate the files at the CIA that
have to do with mind control. And um so I showed
a little bit of uh just what it was like and then
the questions that they ask you because that's
what you have to be prepared for. Um they only
gave us like two and a half weeks to prepare. We
had two and a half weeks before we found out that
we were going to go and I went with my therapist
and one other um girl from New Orleans. And then
another person came from New Mexico and testified.
And um and then there were six other people,
but they were testifying about strictly radiation.
Again, uh we were able to submit as much material
as we wanted ahead of time. Um but you could
only talk for they told you five minutes, but
actually they gave us a little longer. But um we
were told that we had to put everything down and
say it in within five minutes and then leave time
for questions because they did ask you questions.
The reason I left the questions in is because
that was the tough part. The questions, I mean,
it's not that they were hard to answer.
It was just kind of being on the spot,
you know, and not knowing exactly what they
were going to ask you. So, this will give
you a good idea of what kind of things they
might ask, what it would be like. Um, and
uh let's see. And then in the handouts, I just
wanted to mention um the reason I didn't read
or tell you what I what was in my testimony
is because I think it's in here. I put in
um a little bit about the advisory committee. Um
then that's the agenda for the day that we were
testifying. And see, we're down number eight. Um
and then a memorandum from the vice president.
um about the research. Then my therapist um who
talked before um I did and um showed how there
was a link between mind control and radiation and
how the memories had started to come back and the
all the therapists that she had talked to across
the country um their clients were saying the same
thing. I mean, not exactly the same thing, but
it was so similar that it was uncanny. And then
this is my statement. Um, and that's what but I
actually submitted a lot more material than that.
Um, names and places and dates, everything that I
could remember. And then what else is in here? Um,
this is in October, they finally got the final
report of the advisory committee. And this is what
um there's two pages and it was actually
nobody even called us and told us that
they came out with any recommendations but
um I saw it on the internet. Somebody sent
it to me over the by email. Um and you got
to remember that these committees last for
like a year. They meet once a month in different
parts of the country so that they can take you
know public speakers can can come talk and
um they reach every area of the country. Um
and but this had been going on
we were at the very end of it and
um it had been going on since I don't
know April of March or April of um 94.
And then so this is what the recommendations
were. And they did listen to us like I said
because they recommended that um all records
of the CIA bearing on programs of secret human
research such as MK Ultra. Well, you can read it
and that's all the names of the projects that I
could remember. Um they recommended that they
be declassified. So but of course that hasn't
happened yet. Um, and then there's some steps here
to advocate for investigating um, and forming um,
advocacy groups like and I I put in um, Lynn and
Blanch's group um, that they started and this is
kind of and they could correct me if I'm wrong,
but this because because of the um because we you
know kind of put our foot in the door and testify
um, they started ACES the advocacy committee for
human experiment experimental survivors. Okay.
And also uh if you all would like to read the
testimony itself and there's a book by John
Rapapore called US government um mind control
experiments on children. They want to know by
John Rapapore. And in the back of the room there's
um some flyers for how you can order that order
the book. um the documentation which Mr. Um the
man kept asking us about there is documentation.
Um for one thing my memories were considered you
know documentation. Um all the people that
I remembered uh descriptions of places,
people um project names, numbers, medical records,
psychiatric records or from my therapist school
records. We actually went back and verified
that I did miss school at these times that
I remembered. Um actually um in grade school I
probably missed a third of every year and yet I
was never held back. I don't know why. Uh when
family records are considered documentation,
you can go back and talk to relatives who remember
that you were gone at this period of time. Um uh
also remember seeing you bruised or you know being
treated at two lane. My sister remembers that. Um
pictures from childhood my mother kept a scrapbook
and she usually had like two scrapbooks a year
and yet except for two Christmases there's no
Christmas pictures with me in it. There's my
sister, my mother and my father. And I'm not in
any of them because I wasn't there. And birthday,
there's pictures of my sister's birthdays, but
none for me. Um, notes, cards, or anything from
the perpetrators. And they actually did. I got
a Christmas card from Uncle Otto. Remember Uncle
Otto from Deep Creek Lodge? I don't know if he
really wrote it or not. They might have just done
that to um make me feel like, you know, I don't
know. Anyhow, I got a Christmas card from him and
um the magister gave it to me and said Uncle Otto
had sent it. He also gave me a doll, sent me a
doll as a Christmas present, but they took it away
from me. Um any material like harassment material,
which I got quite a bit of and I probably will
when I go home. Um I get it in the mail. I get
it written on my house. So, I have a police come
every time that it's written on the house, my car,
the fence. Uh, it's been written mostly in red
paint, but sometimes blood, animal blood. So,
they're like threats or, you know, just it's just
harassment and um things like die, uh, shut up or
whatever. Um, and so every time that happens, I
have to have the police come out and take pictures
so it it's, you know, documented that I'm getting
it. And then I keep everything um that I get in
the mail. I have a caller ID and call tracer when
I get phone calls. And sometimes I get phone calls
and they'll say words that are supposed to trigger
me and remind me of um you know um things that
happened or call me Crystal, which was my name
at Tulain. Um and also you can you can order
your phone records. Um every month along with my
bill I get every phone call that comes into my
house is written down where it's from. um military
records, um how the memories match the projects
and the experiments, the similarity of stories
between people. Um also, it's a good idea, but
don't ever do this alone, to go back to the sites
if they're still there. And you'd be surprised,
a lot of the buildings are still there. Of course,
too there still going strong. But um you go back
there and take pictures of the places that you
were in or went to, but you don't go alone. I
went with my therapist cuz I was afraid afraid of
going into flashback. Um, but you can use that and
of course the CIA files if we can
get them declassified. And the fact
that the information you can have
validated that there's information
that you know that isn't written in
any book or published anywhere. Um,
and there's just one more thing
that I don't know how much time, but
um, yeah, I'm going to have questions, but I
just wanted to say um, everybody has to decide
for themselves if they want to start talking,
but I think you can see how it's it's important
And it helps the process, the healing process.
It puts you in touch with people that you never
thought you'd meet. Um that you get to know
people that went through the same thing you
did. And that's validation for yourself
cuz that's just as important as you know.
Um you have to decide if the good outweighs the
bad. And I did. And like I said,
I'd do it again in a minute. And
Somebody once said,
"Great spirits have always encountered
violent opposition from mediocre minds."
Great spirits have always encountered
violent opposition from mediocre minds.
We've been listening to Claudia Mullen
Mullen describe her giving testimony at
the presidential hearings on radiation
experiments in March 15th of 95. We are
next going to hear that testimony
and you'll be hearing first Valerie
Wolf who is the therapist of Claudia and
Chris. You'll be hearing Christine Nola
um and then Claudia Mullen um giving their
testimony. You're listening to CKLN 88.1.
Next have a a panel of people who have asked to
present. And again, please uh forgive me if I'm
not pronouncing people's names correctly, but we
have Miss Chris uh De Nola, Miss Valerie Wolf,
and Miss Claudia Mullen. All of Are you all
of New Orleans? Yes. Is that correct? Yes,
to start. My name is Valerie Wolf. In listening
to the testimony today, it all sounds really
familiar. I am here to talk about a possible link
between radiation and mind control experimentation
that began in the late 1940s. The main reason
that mind control research is being mentioned is
because people are alleging that they were exposed
as children to mind control, radiation drugs, and
chemical experimentation which were administered
by the same doctors who are known to have been
involved in conducting both radiation and mind
control research. Written documentation has been
provided revealing the names of people and the
names of research projects in statements from
people across the country. It is also important
to understand that mind control techniques and
follow-ups into adulthood may have been used to
intimidate these particular research subjects
into not talking about their victimization in
government research. As a therapist for the past
22 years, I have specialized in treating victims
and perpetrators of trauma and their families.
When word got out that I was appearing at this
hearing, nearly 40 therapists across the country,
and I had about a week and a half to prepare,
contacted me to talk about clients who had
reported being subjects in radiation and mind
control experiments. The consistency of people's
stories about the purpose of the mind control and
pain induction techniques such as electric shock,
use of hallucinogens, sensory deprivation,
hypnosis, dislocation of limbs, and sexual abuse
is remarkable. There is almost nothing published
on this aspect of mind control used with children.
And these clients come from all over the country
having had no contact with each other. What was
startling was that therapists reported many
of these clients were also physically ill with
autoimmune problems, thyroid problems, multiple
sclerosis, and other muscle and connective tissue
diseases as well as mysterious ailments for which
a diagnosis cannot be found. While somatization
disorder is commonly found in these clients,
many of the clients who've been involved in
the human experimentation with the government
have multiple medically documented physical
ailments. And I was really shocked today to hear
one of the speakers talk about the cysts and the
teeth breaking off because I have a client that
that's happening to. Many people are afraid to
tell their doctors their histories as mind control
subjects for fear of being considered to be crazy.
These clients have named some of the same people,
particularly a Dr. Green who was associated with
clients reports of childhood induction of pain,
mind control techniques, and childhood sexual
abuse. One of my clients who had seen him with a
name tag identified him as Dr. L. Wilson Green.
a person with this same name was the scientific
director of the chemical and radiological
laboratories at the Army Chemical Center and that
he was engaged in doing research for the Army and
other intelligence agencies. Other names that
have come to light are Dr. Sydney Gotle and Dr.
Martin Or who it is reported were also involved
in radiation research. It needs to make be made
clear that people have remembered these names and
events spontaneously with free recall and without
the use of any memory retrieval techniques such
as hypnosis. As much as possible, we have tried to
verify the memories with family members, records,
and experts in the field. Many attempts have been
made through Freedom of Information Act filings
to gain access to the mind control research
documentation. These requests have generally been
slowed down or denied. Although some information
has been obtained, which suggests that at least
some of the information supplied by these clients
is true, it is important that we obtain all of
the information contained in the CIA and military
files to verify or deny our clients memories.
Although many of the files for MK Ultra may
have been destroyed, whatever is left along with
the files for other projects such as Bluebird and
Artichoke, to name only two, contain valuable
information. Furthermore, if as the evidence
suggests, some of these people were used in
radiation experiments, there might be information
in the mind control experiment files on radiation
experiments. We need this information to help in
the rehabilitation and treatment of many people
who have severe psychological and medical problems
which interfere with their social, emotional,
and financial well-being. Finally, I urge you
to recommend an investigation into these matters.
Although there was a commission on mind control,
it did not include include experiments on
children because most of them were too young
or still involved in the research in the late
1970s to come forward. The only way to end the
harassment and suffering of these people is to
make public what has happened to them in the
mind control experiments. Please recommend that
there be an investigation and that the files be
opened on the mind control experiments as
they related to children. Thank you. And
I'm Chris Dakola, born July of 1962, rendering me
32 years of age. I was a subject in radiation as
well as mind control and drug experiments
performed by a man I knew as Dr. Green.
My parents were divorced around 1966 and Donald
Richard Edner, my natural father, was involved
with Dr. Green in the experiments. I was a
subject from 1966 to 1976. Dr. Green performed
radiation experiments on me in 1970, focusing
on my neck, throat, and chest. 1972, focusing
on my chest and my uterus in 1975. each time I
became dizzy, nauseous, and threw up. All these
experiments were performed on me in conjunction
with mind control techniques and drugs in Tucson,
Arizona. Dr. Green was using me mostly as a mind
control subject from 1966 to 1973. His objective
was to gain control of my mind and train me to be
a spy assassin. The first significant memory took
place at Kansas City University in 1966. Don Edner
took me there by plane when my mom was out of
town. I was in what looked like a laboratory and
there seemed to be other children. I was strapped
down naked spread eagle on a table on my back. Dr.
Green had electrodes on my body including my head.
He used what looked like an overhead projector
and repeatedly said he was burning different
images into my brain while a red light flashed
aimed at my forehead. In between each sequence,
he used electric shock on my body and told me to
go deeper and deeper deeper while repeating each
image would go deeper into my brain and I would do
whatever he told me to do. I felt drugged because
he had given me a shot before he started the
procedure. When it was over, he gave me another
shot. The next thing I remember, I was with my
grandparents again in Tucson, Arizona. I was
four years old. You can see from this experiment
that Dr. Green used trauma, drugs, post-hypnotic
suggestion, and more trauma in an effort to gain
total control of my mind. He used me in radiation
experiments both for the purposes of determining
the effects of radiation on various parts of my
body and to terrorize me as an additional trauma
in the mind control experiments. The rest of the
experiments took place in Tucson, Arizona out
in the desert. I was taught how to pick locks,
be secretive, use my photographic memory, and a
technique to withhold information by repeating
numbers to myself. Dr. Green moved on to wanting
me to kill dolls that look like real children.
I stabbed a doll with a spear once after being
severely traumatized, but the next time I refused.
He used many pain induction techniques, but as
I got older, I resisted more and more. He often
tied me down in a cage, which was near his office.
Between 1972 and 1976, he and his assistants were
sometimes careless and left the cage unlocked.
Whenever physically possible, I snuck into his
office and found files with reports and memos
addressed to CIA and military personnel. Included
in these files were project, sub project, subject,
and experiment names with some code numbers for
radiation and mind control experiments which I
have submitted in your written documentation.
I was caught twice and Dr. Green ruthlessly
used electric shock drugs, spun me on a table,
put shots in my stomach and my back, dislocated
my joints and hypnotic techniques to make me
feel crazy and suicidal. Because of my rebellion
and growing lack of cooperation, they gave up on
me as a spy assassin. Consequently, the last two
years, 1974 to 1976, Dr. Green used various mind
control techniques to reverse the spy assassin
messages to self-destruct and death messages.
His purpose he wanted me dead and I struggled to
stay alive all of my adult life. All of my adult
life. I believe it is by the grace of God that I
am still alive. These horrible experiments have
profoundly affected my life. I developed multiple
personality disorder because Dr. Green's goal was
to split my mind into as many parts as possible
so he could control me totally. He failed,
but I've had to endure years of constant physical,
mental, and emotional pain. Even to this day,
I've been in therapy consistently for 12 years.
And it wasn't until I found my current therapist
two and a half years ago who had knowledge of the
mind control experiments that I finally been able
to make real progress and begin to heal. In
closing, I ask that you keep in mind that the
memories I've described are but a glimpse of the
countless others that took place over the 10 years
between 1966 and 1976. that they weren't just
radiation but mind control and drug experiments
as well. I have included more detailed information
of what I remember in your written documentation.
Please help us by recommending an investigation
and making the information available so that
therapists and other mental health professionals
can help more people like myself. Please help us
in an effort to prevent these heinous acts from
continuing in the future. Thank you very much.
Good afternoon. Between the years of 1957 and
1984, I became a pawn in a government scheme whose
ultimate goal was mind control and to create the
perfect spy. All through the use of chemicals,
radiation, drugs, hypnosis, electric shock,
isolation in tubs of water, sleep deprivation,
brainwashing, verbal, physical, emotional, and
sexual abuse. I was exploited unwittingly for
nearly three decades of my life. and the only
explanations given to me were that quote the
end justifies the means and quote I was serving my
country in their bold effort to fight communism. I
can only summarize my circumstances by saying they
took an already abused seven-year-old child and
compounded my suffering beyond belief. The saddest
part is I know for a fact that I was not alone.
There were countless other children in my same
situation and there was no one to help us until
now. I've already submitted as much information
as possible including conversations uh overheard
of the people agencies responsible. I'm able to
report all this to you in such detail because of
my photographic memory and the arrogance of the
doctors the arrogance of the people involved.
They were certain they would always control my
mind. Although the process of recalling these
atrocities is not an easy one, nor is it without
some danger to myself and my family, I feel the
risk is worth taking. Dr. L. Wilson Green, who
claimed to have received $50 million from the
Edgewood Chemical and Radiology Laboratory as
part of the TSD or technical science division of
the CIA once described to Dr. Charles Brown that
quote, "Children were used as subjects because
they were more fun to work with and cheaper, too.
They needed lower profile subjects than soldiers
or government people. So only young willing
females would do. Besides, he said, I like scaring
them. They in the agency think I'm a god creating
subjects experiments for whatever deviant purposes
Sid and James can think of." Sid being Dr. Sydney
got James Dr. James Hamilton. In 1958, I was to be
tested, they told me, by some important doctors,
but from the society or the human ecology society.
And I was instructed to cooperate. I was told not
to look at anyone's faces and not try hard not to
ignore to try hard not to ignore any names as this
was a very secret project. But I was told to be
brave and all these things would help me forget.
Naturally, as most children do, I did the opposite
and remembered as much as I could. Dr. John Ginger
tested me, Dr. Cameron gave me the shocks, and Dr.
Green the X-rays. Then I was told by Sid Godly
that, quote, I was ripe for the big A, or meaning
artichoke. By the time I left to go home, just
like every time from then on, I would remember
only whatever explanations Dr. Robert G. Heath
two-lane medical university gave me for the odd
bruises, needle marks, burns on my head, fingers,
and even the genital soreness. I had no reason to
believe otherwise. They had already begun to
control my mind. The next year, I was sent to
a lodge in Maryland called Deep Creek Cabins to
learn how to sexually please men. I was taught
how to coersse them into talking about themselves.
And it was Doc, it was uh Richard Helms who was
deputy director of the CIA, Dr. Gotlib, uh Captain
George White, Morris Allen, who all planned on
filming as many high government agency officials
and heads of academic institutions and foundations
as possible so that later when the fund funding
for mind control and radiation started to dwindle,
projects would continue. I was used to ent
trap many unwitting men, including themselves,
all with the use of a hidden camera. I was only
9 years old when this sexual humiliation began.
I overheard conversations about a part of the
agency called ORD, which I found out was Office
of Research and Development. It was run by
Dr. Green, Dr. Steven Aldridge, Martin Or,
and Morris Allen. Once a crude remark was made
by Dr. Gotlip about a c possible leak over New
Orleans East involving a large group of [__]
children who are being given massive doses of
radiation. He asked why was Wilson so worried
about a few [__] kids? After all, they would be
the least likely to spill the beans. Another time
I heard Dr. Martin Or who was the director then of
the scientific office and later the head of the
institute for experimental research state that
quote in order to keep more funding coming from
different sources for radiation and mind control
projects. He suggested stepping up the amounts of
stressors used and also the blackmail portion of
the experiments. He said it needed to be done
faster than to get rid of the subjects or they
were asking for us to come back later and haunt
them with our remembrances. There's much more I
could tell you about government sponsored research
including project names, sub project numbers,
people involved, facilities used, test, and other
forms of pain induction. But I think I've given
more than enough information to recommend further
investigation of all the mind control projects,
especially as they involve so much use of the
radiation. I would love nothing more than to say
that I dreamed of this up and need just to forget
it. But that would be a tragic mistake. It would
also be a lie. All these atrocities did occur
to me and to countless other children and all
under the guise of defending our country. It is
because of the cumulative effects of exposure to
radiation, chemicals, drugs, pain, and subsequent
mental and physical distress that I've been robbed
of the ability to work and even to bear any
children of my own. It is blatantly obvious
that none of this was needed, nor should it ever
have been allowed to take place at all. And the
only means we have to seek out the awful truth
and bring it to light is by opening whatever files
remain on all the projects and through another
presidential commission on mind control. I believe
that every citizen of this nation has the right to
know just what is fact and what is fiction. It is
our greatest protection against the possibility
of this ever happening again. In conclusion,
could could I ask either of you, where were your
parents through all this? Uh how do you have any
idea how you were recruited in the first place?
Uh did they did do you have parents and did your
parents know anything about what was going on?
Um I can uh make a brief statement on that. Um
it was my father who was involved uh with Dr.
Green. Um my mother was not aware because they
were divorced when I was 4 years old. Um well
before that separated and uh what would happen,
how he gained access to me is these experiments
took place actually in the middle of the night.
and uh he would uh sneak in while my mom was
asleep, take me out and uh she had absolutely
no knowledge of what happened. However, when
these memories did surface and I began to tell
her about them, uh she there she there was no
question in her mind that he was uh capable. Uh
he had been in the military, in the Air Force,
he had access to have to meet Dr. Green. So
um in answer to your question um it was my father
uh he groomed me from the very beginning started
sexually abusing me from the very beginning and uh
it was just something that he wanted to do and uh
he was closely involved with Dr. Green but my mom
had no knowledge. The only thing she knew was that
she wanted to get away from him. She didn't know
why. She just knew she had to get away from him
because of my reaction to him. I'm sorry. I didn't
mean to go on. Thank you. Thank you. You want an
answer from me also? That's up to you. If you want
um the way I got involved was I was adopted when
I was 2 and a half by a woman who sexually abused
me. And then um she was a friend of the chairman
of the board of Tulain University at the time. And
uh as a favor to him, she I began to show symptoms
of uh you know typical of childhood abuse when
I was very very young. Uh and she asked him to
recommend a psychiatrist and he recommended Dr.
Heath who was involved with the project already.
And so when he discovered that I had already been
abused from the time I was practically born and
that I was had the ability to dissociate and that
I had almost perfect recall and I passed all the
personality tests that they gave me. He suggested
me for the project and so that's how that's into
it. My father had no idea and he died when I
was very young but I I don't know if my mother
knew or not. I don't think she really cared to
tell you the truth. And then she died when I was
a teenager. So after that they had access to me
in the north. Lois, um you mentioned that there
are others across the country who are coming who
are recalling similar things. Yes. Um do they all
cover the same time span generally or do you have
a feel for that? Yeah, generally they're covering
the same time span from about the late 1940s um
until see one of the things that we're hearing
about is people that were assigned to monitor them
in case they should start to remember because it's
so horrible what was done. So, we're not exactly
sure when the actual experimentation took place
and when it got into just the monitoring to make
sure that they were still under control and not
everybody is being monitored. So, but yeah, pretty
much I think it's from the late 40s through the
1970s and maybe even even into 1984 later than
that I found out because after my parents died and
uh there was no one to protect me. the monitor
that she spoke of that my particular monitor was
a was a physician at Tula University and so he
he was a family friend also of my mother's and
he just kept on making sure that I kept going back
and forgetting so it's kind of unclear as to when
whether it stopped or whether it you know where
that where that they still monitor you though
that's why it's I am taking some danger in coming
here today because I'm still being alive. I know
this sounds unbelievable, but I mean there's
actual um she gets stuff in the mail. She gets
phone calls. Um people have been writing things
on her house using the pseudonym that they used
when she was at two lane and only they would know
that name. My real name was never used ever in
anything. So were were they all children at the
time when they when they were Yes, all children.
And the thing is is as therapists we are trying
really hard to figure this out and to get as many
much information as we can. Claudia's memories
have been verified a lot of them because the way
I've approached this is I don't read in the field.
I don't and so as people give me information I
send them to experts like Alan Shefflin who has
a lot of information and then he'll get back to
me to confirm or deny. He has never denied any
information that I've sent him. Some of it can't
be because we don't have all the information, but
a lot of Claudia's memories have been validated
and they're not in any published source. The only
way she would know the things she knows is if she
filed Freedom of Information Act information and
this is what Alan Shefflin is telling me. So I
have and then I've been very careful not to know
a whole lot. So if someone tells me something,
I don't even cue them that because I don't know
either. Duncan, it seems to me that documentary
documentary evidence is going to be key to
establishing the truth of these claims. Yes,
absolutely. Uh it's hard for me to imagine that
a program as as as large and as complex as as
you people have described could have gone on for
so long without a great deal of documentation.
The question is where is this documentation now?
Uh it becomes a catch 22 if it is said that all of
the documentation resides within the CIA files and
all of it secret and they won't give it to us. But
uh what you've described is a pattern of a very
complex organization with doc which involves
plenty of people outside of the CIA as well. Uh
therefore there must be substantial amount of
documentation which could be discovered. uh you
just mentioned uh the the letters that some of
you are still receiving. There is a leap to
documentation. Can you describe for me what
efforts have been made either by yourselves or by
other people who are working on the story to try
to track down some of this documentation and and
what you meant a moment ago when you said that
some of these memories have been uh verified
or validated. Okay. Um Dr. Alan Shefflin and
you have his uh resume in the documentation
and a statement from him about Claudia um in
your in your documentation. He has been for the
past 20 years filing Freedom of Information Act
uh filings to get this information has pieces
been piecing it together. Other people across
the country have been doing the same going back
to the government files getting what they can. Um,
and what they've also been doing is writing books,
sharing information. So, he has actual Freedom of
Information Act information. The problem is
that it's when the requests are going in now,
they're being slowed down or denied or just kind
of lost in the shuffle and the information is
very difficult to get. I'm sorry. I don't
see the documentation in the package that
that was provided to me. Is is there something
missing? I have I supplied uh project numbers. I
sent a a a packet of documentation um overnight
mail. It should have been here Monday and some
more yesterday. So it maybe isn't Well, if we
haven't received it, we'll let you know. Okay.
I sent the first one to Steve Clayman and the
second one to Kristen Cra. We have you. Yeah,
we have some of them. Okay. and and again it was
you know what I could pull together in about a
week and a half from across the country but the
the consistency of the stories and the thing is we
want to verify so Allen has amassed over 20 years
from freedom of information act from memos other
people give him or sharing information uh a lot of
information but we don't have the complete story
there's still a lot of stuff that we don't know
and that's what we're trying to find out because
um Does any of this documentation specifically
refer to radiation experiments? Because we are
told by CIA that they never did any
radiation experiments or so uh what
we need is documentation in order to pursue that.
All you have to do is look up anything on or the
uh the one that I mentioned that I overheard them
speaking about that was almost strictly radiation
and that was run by Dr. Steven Aldridge, Martin
Or and and that's included in the package which
you sent Steve. Yes, I gave and I gave you project
numbers, project names, sub project numbers, even
the subjects. We were given numbers ourselves for
each specific experiment and I overheard my number
because they would they would assume that uh they
would use techniques so that you would forget
assume you know when you go home you wouldn't
remember what happened. So they just talked
freely in front of me. That's why no one ever
hid their face, wore a mask or anything because
they knew that I would not remember and I didn't I
didn't remember until two years ago. I didn't also
with I think you could follow up on Dr. L. Wilson
Green. I don't know if you've come across him,
but he seems to have been involved in both. And I
think realistically in terms of the mind control,
some of the subjects were used in mind control and
radiation. Some, as you've been hearing, have been
strictly radiation and some were strictly mind
control. Um, I think the reason it's coming up
now is because in some of the stuff people are
remembering, they knew that it would break down.
Um, they really worked hard to induce amnesia
and they knew it would break down. And I think
in the last couple years that that's what's been
happening because we're hearing more and more and
um, you know, um, so we're just trying to find out
what's happening here. That's so we'd appreciate
any help you could give us on that. Did you want
to make Yes, I did. Um, I just wanted to address
you for a moment. Uh, the question you asked about
the uh uh documentation on radiation specifically
included in my packet. Um, and I don't know
if you have that or not. Um, there's uh it's
entitled radiation file information. their names
of subject names, experiment names, and some code
numbers that I remember. And uh the problem is we
have no way of uh verifying this without opening
the files. I mean I I believe you have Yeah. You
have what she remembers and you have what Claudia
Do you have the documentation? All I have from
you is uh your three-page four page three page
document whole packet of information. We we can
clarify that. That's I gather the staff has it
so we can look into it after we can clarify what
we don't have what you do have and whatever it is
we can put together and we thank you very much for
your traveling from New Orleans to present to us.
presidential hearings on radiation experiments.
This happened, this testimony took place in March
15th of 1995. Currently, the survivor movement
is calling for uh similar hearings on the mind
control experiments in particular. You've been
listening to the international connection here
on CKLN. going to feature uh more information
uh with uh Valerie Wolf and Claudia Mullen in
upcoming shows. Um if anybody's interested
in getting transcripts of this show of the
with this series and uh we'll be featuring
a an interview with Ronald Howard Cohen,
a writer and survivor of abduction and severe
drugging in the late60s. and uh he has experienced
uh further harassment in attempting to publish
a book about his about his experiences and
uh we'll be continuing this series until
October of 1997 and there's lots more
were subject to human radiation experiment and
some of the advocates who represent them. Their
presence signifies that this administration's
commitment to meeting our obligations of power,
our willingness to share information, to
respect the right of people to know the facts,
the responsibility to limit secrecy,
and that which is truly essential,
and that is to make those who were wronged
and harm whole. When President Clinton came
to Washington, he was dedicated to the task of
rebuilding the relationship of trust between the
citizens and its government. This advisory
committee report, the president's response,
and the actions he will direct many of us to
take today are all evidence of our commitment
and his commitment to rebuild the trust with
the American people. Why did we do this?
Why did the president direct his administration
to open the doors on human radiation experiments?
I believe that this openness puts us in a position
as a nation to close many chapters of the Cold War
just as the president did by ending nuclear
weapons testing for the United States as the
United States and Russia did and pointing our
missiles away from each other and in dismantling
warheads and extending the MPT. And today, another
step of that openness is coming clean on the
human radiation experience. When the president
appointed the advisory committee, he appointed
he committed our whole government to a massive
record search which included some 80 I'm sorry,
some 840,000 pages on the declassification of some
3,020 documents. And we have made available to the
American people these government records because
they strike at the heart of the relationship
between the American people and their government
and whether the government misused individual
citizens. The president committed to do this
without knowing where it would lead or whether
the records would reveal government mistakes,
cause embarrassments or lawsuits. He did this
because he believed that it was the right thing
to do. Today, the president receives from Dr.
Feden and her colleagues on the president's
advisory committee, a report that tells the story
of radiation experiments involving human subjects
funded by the government. We did not realize
when we began this journey the difficulty of the
charge given these citizens, imminent ethicists,
physicians, scientists, citizens, even lawyers.
For the past 18 months, the advisory committee
members and their staff have devoted much
of their lives to this investigation. They
sacrificed their weekends, their vacations, and
late hours. And in the end, for the committee,
their actual working days to review the
documents going back for decades. Today,
they give us their best judgment as to whether
persons were wronged. The nation owes to them,
to their families, and to all the staffs that have
worked on this issue, the generous gratitude for
their public service, and most importantly for the
recommendations which the president will receive
shortly. And most of all, we owe a gracious thanks
to the family members who are here. Dr. Fayen
Mr. President, Secretary Olyri, Attorney General
Reno, Secretary Shala, other members of the human
radiation inter agency working group. On behalf
of my 13 colleagues on the advisory committee,
I am proud to submit our final report. We worked
extremely hard over the last 18 months in order
to inform you and the American people about what
really happened to radiation research subjects
in the Cold War period. With the assistance of
federal agencies, private research centers and
hospitals and numerous citizens, we have assembled
and reviewed hundreds of thousands of documents,
many of which were previously secret.
In 31 days of open hearings conducted
in Washington and throughout the country, we
have heard from hundreds of public witnesses,
we have found that wrongs were indeed committed
both with experiments involving radiation and
with intentional releases of radiation into
the environment. In the pursuit of peace and
the advancement of medicine, certainly to laudable
goals, the rights and interests of individuals and
communities were sometimes ignored. We found
that government officials and physicians who
had the trust of the public and of their patients
abused that trust. Patients were used as subjects
of experiments without their knowledge or consent.
Information was withheld from affected communities
and from the public. Secrets were kept to
protect the government from embarrassment
and legal liability. While the radiation doses
in the experiments we studied were usually low,
and officials and scientists were often concerned
about risk, we do not believe that excuses the
wrongs that were done. We urge you to do the right
thing by those who have been wronged or harmed by
these events. In our report, we recommend for
your consideration guidelines for compensating
former subjects. But if we are to keep faith with
those who have suffered, we must all do more. Your
extraordinary efforts have allowed the American
people to learn about a piece of our history
that we could not otherwise have understood. You
have opened the doors of this nation's records,
and they must stay open. You have recognized
the price of secrecy in research for what it is,
a legacy of cynicism and a legacy of distrust. If
we are to keep faith with those who have suffered,
we must do everything possible to guarantee that
what happened to them never happens again. The
committee learned that research safeguards
have come a long way since the Second World
War. Americans can and should feel much
more secure about medical research today,
but the system remains imperfect. I urge you
to carefully review the committee's findings
and recommendations. Both the government and
research institutions must do all they can
to protect our fellow citizens. If this
committee's work is to mean anything,
it has to be that 50 years from now there does
not have to be another presidential committee
charged with investigating al allegations of
abuses of human subjects. There should never
be another such advisory committee. Information
must not be concealed again from people in their
own time so that it takes two generations for the
truth to come out. Mr. President, your leadership
in this area has been indispensable. Without
your willingness to open government files to
our scrutiny, our work would have been totally
impossible. We could not have done it. Your staff,
your cabinet and agency heads and their staffs
have been supportive at every turn. We have had
every request met, but always with great respect
for our independence. You've set a new standard
for open government in an area that has been
largely secret for 50 years. We on the committee
are both honored and grateful that you have taken
our work so seriously. I hope that we have met the
challenge that you put before us 18 months ago.
On behalf of the committee and of our staff,
thank you for this extraordinary opportunity to
serve our nation. It has been a true privilege.
We have some more people on the committee.
Will the other committee members
uh please stand? Let's give them
all a hand. They did an extraordinary job.
Let me um begin with a simple thank you
to everyone who participated in this
extraordinary project and to everyone who
supported them. Uh I am especially glad to
see here today uh Senator Glenn who's been
so active in working on the medical ethics
issue. Uh Congressman Marky who's worked on this
issue for a very long time. Congressman Frost,
Secretary Shala, Deputy Secretary
of Veterans Affairs, Hershel Gober,
and of course the Attorney General basically tries
to get us all to do the right thing all the time.
I want to thank uh I want to thank Secretary
Olri for her extraordinary devotion to this
cause and you heard in her remarks basically
the the way that she views this. It's a part
of her ongoing commitment to finish the end of the
cold war. and uh perhaps no energy secretary has
ever done as much as she has to be an advocate
whether it is for uh continued reforms within
the energy department or her outspoken endorsement
of the strongest possible commitment on the part
of the United States to a comprehensive testban
treaty which I believe we will achieve next year
in no small measure thanks to the support
of the secretary of energy and of course
uh I want to thank Dr. Ruth Feden uh for her
extraordinary commitment of about a year and
a half of her life to this unusual but important
task. And all of you who served on the committee,
I remember the first time we put this committee
together, I looked I said that's a pretty
distinguished outfit. I wish I could give them
five or six jobs to do. Thank you. I'll expect
you back next Monday and we'll I I do thank you so
much for the work you have done. Let me tell you
that just as this is an important part of u the
efforts that Secretary Olri outlined. I saw this
committee as an indispensable part of our effort
to restore the confidence of the American people
in the integrity of their government. All of these
political reform issues to me are are integrated.
When I became the president, I realized we had
great new economic challenges. We had profound
social problems. that a lot of these things had
to be done by an energized American citizenry,
but that our national government had a role to
play in moving our country through this period
of transition. And in order to do it, we needed
to increase the capacity of the government to
do it through political reform. But we also
needed, as much as anything else, to increase
the confidence of the American people that at
the very least they could trust the United States
government to tell the truth and to do the right
things. So, you have to understand that for me,
one reason this is so important is that I see
it as part of our ongoing effort to give this
government back to the American people. Senator
Glenn's long effort to get Congress to apply to
itself the same laws it imposes on the private
sector. Uh the restrictions that I impose on
members of my administration in high positions
for lobbying for foreign governments. And when the
lobby bill failed in the Congress, I just impose
it by executive order on members of the executive
branch. Uh all these efforts at political reform,
it seems to me, are important. But none of these
efforts can succeed unless people believe that
they can rely on their government to tell them
the truth and to do the right thing. We have
declassified thousands of government documents,
files from the Second World War, the Cold War.
President Kennedy's assassination. These actions
are not only consistent with our national
security, they are essential to advance our
values. So to me, that's what this is all about.
And to all those who represent the families who
have been involved in these incidents, let me say
to you, I hope you feel that your government has
kept its commitment to the American people
to tell the truth and to do the right thing.
We discovered soon after I entered office that
with the spectre of an atomic war looming like
Armageddon far nearer than it does today,
the United States government actually did
carry out on our citizens experiments involving
radiation. That's when I ordered the creation of
this committee. Dr. Feden and the others uh did a
superb job. They enlisted the many of our nation's
most significant and important medical and
scientific ethicists. They had to determine first
whether experiments conducted or sponsored by our
government between 1944 and 1974 met the ethical
and scientific standards of that time and of our
time. And then they had to see to it that our
research today lives up to nothing less than our
highest values and our most deeply held beliefs.
From the beginning, it was obvious to me that
this energetic committee was prepared to do
its part. We declassified thousands of pages of
documents. We gave committee members the keys
to the government's doors, file cabinets,
and safes. For the last year and a half,
the only thing that stood between them, and the
truth were all the late nights and hard work they
had to put in. This report I received today is
a monumental document in more ways than one. But
it is a very very important piece of America's
history and it will shape America's future in
ways that will make us a more honorable,
more successful and more ethical country.
What this committee learned I would like to review
today with a little more detail than Dr. Feden
said because I think it must be engraved on our
national memory. Thousands of government sponsored
experiments did take place at hospitals,
universities, and military bases around our
nation. The goal was to understand the effects of
radiation exposure on the human body. While most
of the tests were ethical by any standards, some
were unethical. Not only by today's standards,
but by the standards of the time in which they
were conducted. They failed both the test of
our national values and the test of humanity. In
one experience, scientist experiment, scientists
injected plutonium into 18 patients without their
knowledge. In another, doctors exposed indigent
cancer patients to excessive doses of radiation,
a treatment from which it is virtually impossible
that they could ever benefit. The report also
demonstrates that these and other experiments were
carried out on precisely those citizens who count
most on the government for its help, the destitute
and the gravely ill. But the dispossessed were not
alone. members of the military, precisely those on
whom we in our government count most. They were
also test subjects. Informed consent means your
doctor tells you the risk of the treatment
you are about to undergo. In too many cases,
informed consent was withheld. Americans were
kept in the dark about the effects of what was
being done to them. The deception extended beyond
the test subjects themselves to encompass their
families and the American people as a whole. For
these experiments were kept secret and they were
shrouded not for a compelling reason of national
security but for the simple fear of embarrassment
and that was wrong. Those who led the government
when these decisions were made are no longer
here to take responsibility for what they did.
They're not here to apologize to the survivors,
the family members, or the communities whose lives
were darkened by the shadow of the atom and these
choices. So today, on behalf of another generation
of American leaders and another generation of
American citizens, the United States of America
offers a sincere apology to those of our citizens
who were subjected to these experiments, to
their families, and to their communities.
When the government does wrong, we have a moral
responsibility to admit it. The duty we owe to
one another to tell the truth and to protect our
fellow citizens from excesses like these is one
we can never walk away from. Our government
failed in that duty and it offers an apology
to the survivors and their families and to all
the American people who must who must be able
to rely upon the United States to keep its word to
tell the truth and to do the right thing. We know
there are moments when words alone are not enough.
That's why I'm instructing my cabinet to use and
build on these recommendations to devise promptly
a system of relief, including compensation that
meets the standards of justice and conscience.
When called for, we will work with Congress to
serve the best needs of those who were harmed.
Make no mistake, as the committee report says,
there are circumstances where compensation is
appropriate as a matter of ethics and principle.
I am committed to seeing to it that the United
States of America lives up to its responsibility.
Our greatness is measured not only in how we
so frequently do right, but also how we act
when we know we've done the wrong thing. how
we confront our mistakes, make our apologies,
and take action. That's why this morning I
signed an executive order instructing every
arm and agency of our government that conducts,
supports, or regulates research involving human
beings to review immediately their procedures
in light of the recommendations of this report
and the best knowledge and standards available
today and to report back to me by Christmas.
I have also created a bioeththics advisory
commission to supervise the process to watch
over all such research and to see to it that
never again do we stray from the basic values
of protecting our people and being straight
with them. The report I received today will
not be left on a shelf to gather dust. Every one
of its pages offers a lesson, and every lesson
will be learned from these good people who put
a year and a half of their lives into the effort
to set America straight. Medical and scientific
progress depends upon learning about people's
responses to new medicines, to new cutting edge
treatments. Without this kind of research, our
children would still be dying from polio and other
killers. Without responsible radiation research,
we wouldn't be making the progress we are in the
war on cancer. We have to continue to research.
But there is a right way and a wrong way to do it.
There are there are local citizens review boards.
There are regulations that establish proper
informed consent and ensure that experiments
are conducted ethically. But in overseeing this
necessary research, we must never relax our
vigilance. The breathtaking advances in science
and technology demand that we always keep our
ethical watch light burning. No matter how rapid
the pace of change, it can never outrun our core
convictions that have stood us so well as a nation
for more than 200 years now through many different
scientific revolutions. I believe we will meet the
test of our times. that as science and technology
evolve, our ethical conscience will grow, not
shrink. Informed consent, community right to know,
our entire battery of essential human protections,
all these grew up in response to the health and
humanitarian crises of this 20th century. They
are proof that we are equal to our challenges.
Science is not ever simply objective. It emerges
from the crucible of historical circumstances and
personal experience. Times of crisis and fear can
call forth bad science, even science we know in
retrospect to be unethical. Let us remember the
difficult years chronicled in this report. And
think about how good people could have done things
that we know were wrong. Let these pages serve as
an internal reminder to hold humility and moral
accountability in higher esteem than we do the
latest development in technology. Let us remember
too that cynicism about government has roots in
historical circumstances because of stonewallings
and evasions in the past. times when a family
member or a neighbor suffered an injustice and
had nowhere to turn and couldn't even get the
facts. Some Americans lost faith in the promise
of our democracy. Government was very powerful
but very far away and not trusted to be ethical.
So today, by making ourselves accountable for the
sins of the past, I hope more than anything else,
we are laying the foundation stone for a new era.
Good people like these members of Congress
who have labored on this issue for a long
time and have devoted their careers to
trying to do the right thing and having
people justifiably feel confidence in the work of
their representatives. They will continue to work
to see that we implement these recommendations.
And under our watch, we will no longer hide the
truth from our citizens. We will act as if all
that we do will see the light of day. Nothing
that happens in Washington will ever be more
important in anyone's life affected by these
experiments perhaps than these reports we issue
today. But all of us as Americans will be better
off because of the larger lesson we learned
in this exercise and because of our continuing
effort to demonstrate to our people that we can
be faithful to their values. Thank you very much.